Guide to the Samuel Franklin Leib Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Samuel Franklin Leib papers
1881-1920
SC0116
Leib, Samuel Franklin, 1848-1924.
10.5 Linear feet (12 boxes)
The collection consists of four major components: Stanford correspondence pertaining to Judge Leib's association with the Stanford family and his responsibilities as a member of the first Board of Trustees of Stanford University (1891-1923); personal correspondence (1885-1910); correspondence pertaining to Leib's fruit and other farm interest (1883-1919); and legal and business correspondence pertaining to his San Jose law practice and local business interests (1881-1920),including cases resulting from the failure of the Savings Bank of San Diego County. Major correspondents include Luther Burbank, John Casper Branner, George Crothers, Horace Davis, Timothy Hopkins, David Starr Jordan, Charles Lathrop, Leland and Jane Stanford, Wilson and Wilson (law firm, San Francisco) and Sarah Winchester.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The collection was given to the Stanford University Archives by Charles Leib, 1972-1981. Additional materials were given by Mrs. Richard Anderson in 2002.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Description of the Collection
The collection consists of four major components: Stanford correspondence pertaining to Judge Leib's association with the Stanford family and his responsibilities as a member of the first Board of Trustees of Stanford University (1891-1923); personal correspondence (1885-1910); correspondence pertaining to Leib's fruit and other farm interest (1883-1919); and legal and business correspondence pertaining to his San Jose law practice and local business interests (1881-1920),including cases resulting from the failure of the Savings Bank of San Diego County. Major correspondents include Luther Burbank, John Casper Branner, George Crothers, Horace Davis, Timothy Hopkins, David Starr Jordan, Charles Lathrop, Leland and Jane Stanford, Wilson and Wilson (law firm, San Francisco) and Sarah Winchester.
Access Terms
Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926.; Crothers, George E. (George Edward), 1870-1957.; Davis, Horace, 1831-1916; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Lathrop, Charles G. (Charles Gardner), 1849-1914.; Leib, Samuel Franklin, 1848-1924.; Savings Bank of San Diego County.; Stanford University. Board of Trustees.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.; Wilson & Wilson (law firm).; Winchester, Sarah.; Agriculture --California.; Practice of law --California.; Ross Affair.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Series 1
  - Stanford Correspondence, 1889-1910; Subseries 1
    Letters are arranged alphabetically by author's last name. Where more than one letter from an individual is included, the letters are further arranged chronologically.
    This subseries includes letters pertaining to Leib's association witht he Stanfords and his responsibilities as a member of the Stanford University Board of Trustees. Major correspondents include David Starr Jordan, Charles Lathrop, George Crothers, John Branner, Timothy Hopkins, the Stanfords, and the Wilson and Wilson law firm of San Francisco. Topics discussed include finalizing the endowment and enfranchising the Board of Trustees; the Stanford amendment; the Ross affair; faculty appointments and salaries; water cases; and other trustee business.
    - Abbott through Berner (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Abbott, Adams, Allardice, Angell, Arden, Berner
    - Branner, J.C., 1900-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      The Branner correspondence covers the following topics: Branner's geological research, local liquor laws, University tax status, establishment of an on-campus public grade school, water rights and lawsuits, establishment of an on-campus University cemetery.
    - Brooke through Cooksey (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Brooke, Brown, Bullock, Butler, Caldwell, Carnegie Foundation, Caton, Clark, Clement, Cooksey
    - Crothers, George E., 1899-1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The Crothers correspondence covers the following topics: campaign for passage of the Stanford Amendment, arrangements for finalizing the endowment, Stanford Alumni Association business and interests, determination of University's legal status and Board of Trustee's corporate identity, composition and duties of the Board of Trustees, various aspects of University budgeting and financial affairs.
    - Cutter through Hodges (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Cutter, Cubberley, W.H. Davis, Horace Davis, Dillman, Dodge, Donaldson, Duniway, Dyer, Eaton, Farrand, Felton, Field, Fischer, Gardner, Gilbert, Godbold, Gorbusier, Gray, Greeves, Halman, Rabey, Harrison, Hawthorne, Hayne, Herrin, Hess, Hodges
    - Hopkins, Timothy, through Jenkins (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Howard, Hull, Jenkins. The Hopkins correspondence covers the following topics: (1894-1910) social and business meetings of the Board of Trustees, near-campus liquor sales, proposed town-to-campus railroad line, medical school's financial difficulties, campus arboretum.
    - Jordan, David Starr, 1891-1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      The Jordan correspondence covers the following topics: professorial appointments, choices of lecturers, invitations to campus formal events, visit of McKinley, library acquisitions, establishment of on-campus public grade school, salaries, Ross Affair, campaign for passage of Stanford Amendment, University fees, water supply, arrangements for finalization of endowment, campus workmen's wages, departure of group of promising young Law School faculty.
    - Jordan, David Starr, 1903-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The Jordan correspondence covers the following topics: liquor question near campus, campus trolley line, formal observations and events, establishment of on-campus public grade school, salary appropriations, invalid students, Palo Alto hospital and sanitarium, typhoid fever epidemic on campus, Student Guild, trade unions controversy> Atkinson-Snodgrass controversy (bicycle rules and regulations), Luther Burbank, automobiles on campus, dances on campus, Professor Ross affair, death of Jane Stanford, Professor Goebel's affair, student discipline, selection of church organist, Medical School facility, Rev. Dr. Brown's nomination for chaplaincy, Forum Club, Faculty Club. [Letters from Dr. Jordan which do not include direct references to Stanford subjects are included in personal correspondence, cf. Box 3, Folder 5 ]
    - Judge through Kirke (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Judge, Kellogg, Kirk, Kirk, Kirke
    - Lathrop, Charles G., 1894-1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      The Lathrop correspondence covers the following topics: Board of Trustees meeting scheduling, deeds to Stanford lands, campaign for passage of Stanford Amendment, water questions (pumps, wells, lawsuits), Lathrop's power of attorney for Jane L. Stanford, Metropolitan Trust Company lawsuit against estate of Jane L. Stanford, University investments, on-campus horse stabling, on-campus light and power generation, establishment of on-campus public grade school, University band, Professor Ross Affair, on-campus sewage disposal system, Professor Loser's "locomobile" affair, professorial salaries, on-campus telephone service, rental of campus facilities, incorporation of Board of Trustees, Jane L. Stanford's personal property taxes, local labor disputes, law library, gift acquisitions, Palo Alto Stock Farm, miscellaneous physical plant problems and policies.
    - Lathrop, Charles G. (1903-1909) through Lawton (Box 2, Folder 1)
      The Lathrop correspondence covers the following topics: arrangements for finalization of Stanford endowment, several on-going water rights suits, reports from the management of Vina Ranch, smaller issues under consideration by the Board of Trustees.
    - Outgoing Letters, 1900-1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      The Leib outgoing correspondence covers the following topics: campus water system, campaign for passage of the Stanford Amendment, management of Vina Ranch, Metropolitan Trust Company lawsuit, numerous legal discussions regarding finalization of endowment and other Trustee matters. Primary addressees are: Charles G. Lathrop, David S. Jordan, George E. Crothers, and the Wilson and Wilson law firm of San Francisco.
    - Leiter through Sotz (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Leiter, Lusk, McMahill, Maddock, Marx, Maurer, Miller, Miscellaneous University form notes, Moore, Mynick, Nash, Newton, Nickel, Niles, O'Neil, Palo Alto Stock Farm, Pardee, Pease, Peterson, Phelan, Piefer, Pitts, Pomeroy, Ponce, Poole, Quinlan, Ramsey, Renner, Rhodes, Scott, Sewall, Shaw, Sheehan, Shepard, Shortridge, Shoup, D. R. Smith, E.H. Smith, Sotz
    - Stanford, Leland and Jane L., 1889-1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      The Stanfords' correspondence includes: five letters from Leland Stanford discussing pre-University judicial questions but establishing basis of the Stanford-Leib acquaintance which led to Leib's association with the University; and, thirty communications from Jane L. Stanford (letters, notes, and telegrams) concerning the University budget, campaign for passage of the Stanford Amendment, Board meetings in the Stanford home, water cases, and the Professor Ross Affair. Some of these communications are signed by Mrs. Stanford, most are both written and signed by her personal secretary.
    - Stillman through Tweed (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Stillman, Stratton, Sturtevant, Suzzallo, Treat, Tweed
    - Vina Ranch through Wilke (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Vina Ranch, Wells, Whaley, Wilbur, Williams, Wilke
    - Wilson and Wilson Law Firm of San Francisco, 1898-1908 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      The Wilson and Wilson correspondence covers the following topics: various water cases and lawsuits, taxation cases, disposal of Jane L. Stanford's bonds, lawsuits arising from near-campus liquor sales question, suits against the Stanford estate, execution of Jane L. Stanford's will.
    - Woods through Wright (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Woods, Woodworth, Wooster, C.F. Wright, Eli Wright
  - Personal Correspondence, 1885-1910; Subseries 2
    This subseries contains letters pertaining to Leib's personal and family life. Included are 140 letters from naturalist Luther Burbank, a close personal friend of Leib's.
    The letters are arranged alphabetically by author's last name. Where more than one letter from an individual is included, the letters are further arranged chronologically.
    - A through Bright (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Alexander, Allman, American Legion of Honor, Archer, "M. B.", Bartlett, Benso, Bowden, Branner, Breyfogle, Bright
    - Burbank, Luther, 1896-1902 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      The Burbank correspondence covers the following topics: grafts and plant specimens exchanged between Burbank and Leib, arrangements for exchange visits to each other's farm, arrangements for Burbank's series of lectures at Stanford and for the attendant honorarium, discussions of horticultural and family incidents and problems.
    - Burbank, Luther, 1903-1910 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      The Burbank correspondence covers the following topics: results of ongoing experiments and research, new ideas in several branches of horticulture, exchange of family news, discussions of each other's health and tendency to overwork. [Note: This file also includes copies of Leib's outgoing letters, some incomplete, written to Burbank during 1905.]
    - C through G (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Campbell, Carthill, "Carnival of Roses" Executive Committee [including letters from committee under former title: "Executive Committee to Prepare a Reception for the President"], Chapin, Combe, Cosmos Club, Croke, Crosby, "D.", Dabney, Davis, deCroy, deG---, Dickey, Driscoll, Eberhard, Gilliland [general agent for Thomas Alva Edison], Emlay, Farrand, Fauley, Ferbos, First Ward Improvement Club, Fischer, Fox, Gardner, Gates, Gausline, Gillet, Gould
    - H through L (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Harkins, Harper, Hatch, Hoskins, Hughes, Hyland, Ingram, Irons, James, Johnson, Johnston, D.S. Jordan [personal correspondence pertaining to travel plans, dinner parties, other social events not directly pertinent to Stanford business], Lampskin, Latimer, Earl Leib, Frank Leib, W.W. Leib, Leuzem, Lewis, The Lincoln Farm Association, The Lincoln Monument League, Linda Vista Golf Club, Lorigan
    - M (Box 3, Folder 6)
      McCann, McPherson, McVeigh, Maloney, Marmolejo, Martin, Mauk, Mitchell Motor Car Company, Charles Moore, L.P. Moore, Moorhead, Mulvema, Murgotten, Mynick
    - N through S (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Newton, Ohio Society of Santa Clara County, Ortley, Paine, Parisian Dyeing Works, Payne, Peters, Ranken, Reed, Rutherford, Sainte Claire Club, Santa Clara College, Santa Clara County Lawyers, Seismological Society of America, Smith and Pressinger Clothiers, Snyder, Sontheimer, Stephens, Stone, Stump, Sullivan, Swift
    - T through Z (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Thomas, Thorne, Trescony, Uncle Remus' Magazine, Unitarian Club, Vanmeter, Villegas, Waldteufel, Welch, Wickson, Wingate, Wright, Young
  - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1883-1919; Subseries 3
    This subseries consists of letters pertaining to Leib's fruit and other farm interests.
    The letters in this subseries are arranged chronologically
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1883-1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1889 Jan-Aug (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1889 Sep-Dec (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1895-1899 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1902-1904 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1905-1907 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Fruit and Agriculture Correspondence, 1908-1919 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1881-1920; Subseries 4
    This subseries includes letters pertaining to Leib's San Jose law practice and local business interests.
    The letters in this subseries are arranged chronologically by year only.
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1892 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 15-17)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 13-15)
    - Legal and Business Correspondence, 1911-1928 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Legal and Business Records, Subseries 5
    The records in this subseries, including bills, receipts, and cancelled checks, are selected samples, chosen on the basis of their representative value, general interest, and state of preservation.
    The records in this subseries are arranged chronologically by year only.
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1883-1892 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1893-1895 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1896-1899 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1900-1906 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1907-1908 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Selected Samples of Legal and Business Records (bills, receipts, cancelled checks, etc.), 1909-1920 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Oversize Legal and Business Records, Subseries 6
    - Deeds, titles, contracts; and hand-written notes (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Journal containing day-by-day account of an oil expedition conducted under Leib's auspices in the Bakersfield area of the San Joaquin Valley, 1900 Apr 13-1901 Nov 30 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      The journal was apparently (judging by the name in the fly-leaf) kept by a George H. Eldridge of the United States Geological Survey. It appears to represent an expedition of both scientific and businessinvestment interest.
  - Additional Correspondence and Business Records, Subseries 7
    The contents of this subseries were added to the collection in May 1976. They include Stanford correspondence, personal correspondence, fruit and agriculture correspondence, and legal and business correspondence. Of particular interest in this subseries is Leib's correspondence with Sarah Winchester (box 10, folders 4 and 5), and with Luther Burbank and his publisher, Binner, from July 1907, to August 1908 (box 10, folder 2).
    - Stanford correspondence, 1905 Nov 1-1906 Apr 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Personal correspondence, 1905 Nov 1-1906 Apr 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Also includes correspondence with Luther Burbank and his publisher, Binner, 1907 Jul-1908 Aug
    - Fruit and agriculture correspondence, 1905 Nov 1-1906 Apr 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Legal and business correspondence, 1905 Nov 1-1905 Dec 31 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Includes correspondence with Sarah Winchester
    - Legal and business correspondence, 1906 Jan 1-1906 Mar 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous business records (receipts, bills, etc.) (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-317
  - Correspondence, Subseries 1
    - Mabury family, estate matters, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Burbank, Luther, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dawson, E. L. (California Fruit Growers Association), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re fruit business, A-J, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence re fruit business, K-W, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence general, A-C, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes correspondence with John Casper Branner and from Clarke & Clarke re estate of John Rock.
    - Correspondence general, D-G, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence with Joseph E. Donaldson re his California citizenship as it relates to attending Stanford and with John W. Gwilt re estate of John Rock.
    - Correspondence general, H-K, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence with Hayes Apperson Company re purchasing automobile.
    - Correspondence general, L-M, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes outgoing letter to Geo. W. Scott re Farmers Union and correspondence with Mayfield Board of Trade re direct road to Stanford campus.
    - Correspondence general, N-S, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes correspondence with Pope Manufacture Company re purchasing automobile.
    - Correspondence general, T-W, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes correspondence with Sherman D. Thacher of Thacher School re Leib's son leaving school and issue of accreditation, and with S. L. Winchester re sale of land.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Subseries 2
    - Golden Gate Packing Company accounts, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Record of loans, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notebook on law, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Savings Bank of San Diego County Failure, Subseries 3
    - Correspondence of S. F. Leib, 1896-1902 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Account books, Hiram Mabury with Bryant Howard, 1885-1888 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letters to Hiram Mabury from San Diego bank, 1884-1890 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters to Hiram Mabury from San Diego bank, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters to Hiram Mabury from San Diego bank, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters to Hiram Mabury from San Diego bank, 1896, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Clippings, 1895-1897 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Legal documents, primarily regarding the failure of the Savings Bank of San Diego County., 1888-1902 (Box 2)